<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>basics on Random thoughts and ideas</title><link>https://lucabruzzone.me/tags/basics/</link><description>Recent content in basics on Random thoughts and ideas</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>All content is under CC BY-SA license. Luca Bruzzone</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 09:05:33 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lucabruzzone.me/tags/basics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is the iPad a laptop?</title><link>https://lucabruzzone.me/posts/is-ipad-a-laptop/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 09:05:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucabruzzone.me/posts/is-ipad-a-laptop/</guid><description>Why did I switched as a main machine to my iPad I switched since almost a year to the iPad as a main machine, this was due to the fact that I already had it, and I found myself using it way much more than my laptop, and I decided to invest some money in a keyboard and call it my main machine from that moment on.
What I discovered is that, for certain workload, it was actually helping me to focus, thanks to the different way of thinking about computing that the iPad has.</description></item><item><title>What are cookies anyway?</title><link>https://lucabruzzone.me/posts/what-are-cookies-anyway/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 08:00:54 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucabruzzone.me/posts/what-are-cookies-anyway/</guid><description>This is a bit of a technically lighter explanation meant for not technical people to try to understand what is a cookie and why should you even care about it.
Disclaimer for technical people, to boil it down, some stuff will be purposely slightly inaccurate, or more reflective of HTTP 1 instead of HTTP 2. But for the sake of understanding why cookie matters or not, it&amp;rsquo;s irrelevant.
A web server doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily remember you To understand the need for cookies, what you need to know at the beginning, is the fact that every time that you reload a page, the &amp;ldquo;website&amp;rdquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily know if you reload three times, or you are three different people.</description></item></channel></rss>